Milislav Demerec Papers 1919-1966 Mss.B.D394
American Philosophical Society
Milislav Demerec Papers
1919-1966
Mss.B.D394
American Philosophical Society
14.25 Linear feet
The geneticist Milislav Demerec emigrated from Yugloslavia in 1919, spending nearly his entire career in the Department of Genetics at Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory. Working initially on the genetics of maize and later on Drosophila virilis, his research interests included radiation and chemical mutagenesis, and during the Second World War, penicillin and the genetics of antibiotic resistance. Demerec served as head of the laboratory at Cold Spring Harbor from 1941 until 1960. The Demerec collection contains the extant professional papers of Milislav Demerec, dating primarily from the time of his arrival at Cold Spring Harbor until his retirement. In addition to his correspondence with colleagues, the collection includes interesting material on the administration of Cold Spring Harbor laboratory during the 1940s and 1950s, data and research notes, material relating to professional organizations (e.g. Genetics Society of America, American Society of Naturalists), a lengthy series of lectures given by Demerec, and a large number of photographs pertaining to Demerec's research, but also to his colleagues and Cold Spring Harbor itself. There is also a Register of visitors to the laboratory (1927-1945) and a Milislav Demerec reprint list.
Demerec, M., (Milislav), 1895-1966
Other Finding Aids note
The printed version of Bentley Glass' A Guide to the Genetics Collections of the American Philosophical Society contains another biography of Demerec and a further description of the Demerec Papers.
Bibliography
Glass, Bentley, "Milislav Demerec," Biographical Memoirs of the National Academy of Sciences 47 (1971), 1-21.
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
Milislav Demerec came to the United States from Yugoslavia in 1919 and joined the Department of Plant Breeding at Cornell, where he studied variegation of maize. In 1923 Demerec began his career at Cold Spring Harbor as a staff member of the Department of Genetics of the Carnegie Institution of Washington, later expanding his research interests to include studies of Delphiniums, Drosophila, and radiation genetics.
In the early 1940s Demerec became director of the Long Island Biological Association Laboratory and the Department of Genetics. Under his leadership the two scientific groups were in effect combined, and Cold Spring Harbor became an institution where genetics intersected with research in physico-chemical biology. It was a center especially noted for its summer phage courses and symposia in quantitative biology. By the time of Demerec's retirement in 1960, Cold Spring Harbor had become an international center of molecular biology.
Unfortunately there are no files on the summer symposia, but there is some related material. In order to organize summer research and conferences, Demerec communicated with researchers from several areas in the life sciences. Therefore, in addition to files on his activities in classical genetics-professional organizations, lectures, correspondence with geneticists, and over sixty laboratory notebooks -- the Demerec Collection contains records of his involvement with the new physico-chemical biology, and material on conferences and international congresses.
Abramson, Harold Alexander, 1899-1980 Correspondence (6 items) 1945-1946 English
Babcock, Ernest Brown, 1877-1954 ( Includes correspondence regarding the genetics of plants (Delphinium and Crepis), the International Congress of Genetics, and the National Academy of Sciences.) Correspondence (22 items) 1930-1946 English
Beadle, George Wells, 1903-1989 ( Includes correspondence regarding maize genetics, drosophila genetics, recommendations.) Correspondence (2 folders (33 items)) 1929-1958 English
Blakeslee, Albert Francis, 1874-1954 ( Includes correspondence regarding the Carnegie Institution of Washington, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, drosophila genetics, and World War II.) Correspondence (6 folders (119 items)) 1927-1944 English
Bridges, Calvin B. (Calvin Blackman), 1889-1938 ( Includes correspondence regarding drosophila genetics, research support, and publications.) Correspondence (7 folders (182 items)) 1932-1949 English
Bronk, Detlev W. (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975 Correspondence (3 items) 1953-1960 English
Caspari, Ernst W. Correspondence (4 items) 1955-1960 English
Castle, William E. (William Ernest), 1867-1962 Correspondence (5 items) 1933-1948 English
Condon, Edward Uhler, 1902-1974 Correspondence (6 items) 1947-1948 English
Davenport, Charles Benedict, 1866-1944 ( Includes correspondence regarding Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, International Congress of Genetics, laboratory techniques and equipment, research support, and publications.) Correspondence (2 folders (45 items)) 1921-1942 English
Delbruck, Max Correspondence (6 items) 1946-1953 English
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975 ( Includes correspondence regarding drosophila genetics, population genetics, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, the Atomic Energy Commission, research support, and publications.) Correspondence (7 folders (171 items)) 1929-1957 English
Emerson, Rollins Adams, 1873-1947 ( Includes correspondence regarding maize genetics, genetics of plants, and drosophila genetics.) Correspondence (2 folders (115 items)) 1923-1947 English
Ephrussi, Boris, 1901-1971 ( Includes correspondence regarding Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, conferences and symposia, and World War II.) Correspondence (40 items) 1934-1961 English
Goldschmidt, Richard, 1878-1958 Correspondence (4 items) 1941-1951 English
Haldane, J. B. S. (John Burdon Sanderson), 1892-1964 Correspondence (6 items) 1931-1961 English
Hollaender, Alexander, 1898-1986 ( Includes correspondence regarding drosophila genetics, yeast, neurospora, and penicillium.) Correspondence (75 items) 1939-1958 English
Metz, Charles William, 1889-1975 ( Includes correspondence regarding Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, drosophila genetics, and the International Congress of Genetics.) Correspondence (4 folders (116 items)) 1920-1955 English
Moe, Henry Allen, 1894-1975 Correspondence (3 items) 1928-1956 English
Muller, H. J. (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967 ( Includes correspondence regarding drosophila genetics, cytogenetics, human genetics, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, World War II, and the International Congress of Genetics.) Correspondence (3 folders (70 items)) 1926-1948 English
Sonneborn, Tracy M., 1905-1981 Correspondence (6 items) 1947-1960 English
Stadler, L. J. (Lewis John), 1896-1954 ( Includes correspondence regarding maize genetics, barley, radiation genetics, and political issues.) Correspondence (47 items) 1926-1949 English
Stanley, Wendell M. (Wendell Meredith), 1904-1971 Correspondence (3 items) 1940-1947 English
Sturtevant, Alfred Henry, 1891-1970 ( Includes correspondence regarding drosophila genetics, genetics of plants, conferences and symposia, and recommendations.) Correspondence (2 folders (45 items)) 1926-1943 English
Timofeev-Resovskii, N. V. (Nikolai Vladimirovich), 1900-1981 ( Includes correspondence regarding Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, International Congress of Genetics, drosophila genetics, and fellowships.) Correspondence (2 folders (46 items)) 1930-1948 English
Tuve, Merle Antony, 1901-1982 ( Includes correspondence regarding the Carnegie Institution of Washington, radiation genetics, drosophila genetics, and Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory.) Correspondence (35 items) 1936-1940 English
Urey, Harold Clayton, 1893-1981 Correspondence (2 items) 1948 English
Related Archival Materials note
Several collections at the APS include material relating to the biological laboratories at Cold Spring Harbor, including the papers of Charles B. Davenport (B D27) and Albert Blakeslee (B B585), and the Records of the Eugenics Record Office (Ms. Coll. 77).
Demerec appears as a correspondent in the papers of Max Bergmann (B B445), Ernst Caspari (Ms. Coll. 1), Charles B. Davenport (B D27), L.C. Dunn (B D917), Theodosius Dobzhansky (B D65), Hubert Dana Goodale (B G61), Michael Lerner (B L563), Warren Lewis (B L586), Robert Cushman Murphy (B M957), James V. Neel (Ms. Coll. 96), Thomas Rivers (B R52), Peyton Rous (B R77), and Jack Schultz (Ms. Coll. 27).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Mary Demerec, 1966 (accession numbers 1969-1429ms, 1430ms)
Scope and Contents note
The Demerec Papers provide almost complete documentation of the professional life of the geneticist Milislav Demerec.
The collection is very sparse for the period of Demerec's career prior to his emigration to America, however later, and especially after the Second World War, he took an active interest in the state of scientific institutions in Yugoslavia. His correspondence with C.B. Hutchinson, Mirko Koric, Peo Koller, Barna, Gyorffy, and the American Association for Reconstruction in Yugoslavia offer insight into the state of post-war genetics in Demerec's home country, and particularly into the impact of Lysenko in Eastern Europe.
The course of Demerec's early years in the United States, spent at Cornell, are documented in letters with R.A. Emerson and Allen C. Fraser, but the bulk of the correspondence dates from after his move to Cold Spring in 1923.
Demerec's early study of the genetic effects of x-ray in Drosophila is Theodore S. Painter, Margaret Hoover, B.P. Kaufmann, and Eileen Sutton, and in folders labeled Gene Study Organization. Some of his extensive correspondence with Calvin B. Bridges, and therefore with Thomas Hunt Morgan's group at Cal Tech, includes discussions of Bridges' work in mapping of the giant salivary chromosomes of D. melanogaster, though most pertains to their joint concern in the Drosophila Information Service that they cofounded.
The occasional competitive tensions between the laboratories at Cal Tech and Cold Spring can be gleaned from Demerec's correspondence with Walter Gilbert, but particularly in his exchanges with Theodosius Dobzhansky and L. C. Dunn.
Series I. Correspondence, 1919-1966 11.5 linear feet
Series II. Diplomas and awards, 1916-1966 0.5 linear feet
Series III. Laboratory notes, ca.1930s-1940s 1.5 linear feet
Series IV. Photographs ca.1922-1960
Biographical/Historical note
Born in Yugoslavia in 1895, the geneticist Milislav Demerec graduated from the College of Agriculture at Krizevci in 1916, remaining there are as an adjunct at the Experiment Station until 1919. With the war ended, however, Demerec emigrated to the United States and accepted a position in the Department of Plant Breeding at Cornell University. For four years, he worked under R. A. Emerson, studying the genetic basis of such phenotypic traits in maize as variegation and viriscence of seedlings manifesting somatic mosaicism.
In 1923, Demerec left Cornell for Cold Spring Harbor, where his most productive years of research followed. Beginning as a member of the staff of the Department of Genetics of the Carnegie Institution, he was eventually promoted to Director of the Long Island Biological Association Laboratory in 1941, and of Carnegie's Department of Genetics in 1943. A superlative administrator, under Demerec's watch, the Biological Association and Department of Genetics were effectively combined, and Demerec remained in charge of both until his retirement in 1960. His tenure saw the establishment of the important summer meetings at Cold Spring Harbor, out of which grew the courses in bacteriophage and bacterial genetics. From 1941 to 1960, he organized the equally important Symposium in Quantitative Biology and the summer training courses for geneticists. Part of Demerec's legacy is founded as well in his editorial work on the publications stemming from the Symposia, as well as the Drosophila Guide, The Biology of Drosophila, Advances in Genetics, and the Drosophila Information Service. Demerec was active as well in organizing the International Congresses of Genetics from the 7th Congress in Edinburgh, 1938, through the 11th Congress, 1960.
As a researcher at Cold Spring Harbor, Demerec shifted away from plant genetics to attempts to assess factors regulating mutation rates in Drosophila virilis and to assessing mutation rates at different ontogenetic stages. With H. J. Muller in 1918, he had been involved in some of the earliest efforts to determine whether genetic mutations could be artificially induced, and at Cold Spring during the 1930s, he ramped up his program in radiobiology to a large scale, working on x-ray induced mutations in Drosophila melanogaster. During the 1940s, he explored the role of ultraviolet rays and neutrons in mutation, working in conjunction with M. A. Tuve's laboratory in the Dept. of Terrestrial Magnetism at the Carnegie Institution, and he became increasingly interested in variation in spontaneous mutation rates in D. melanogaster. Demerec helped to establish the existence of mutator genes, and his interests in unstable genes led to an exploration of position effects influencing mutation.
The exigencies of the Second World War led Demerec to a third phase in his research, working on the bacteria Escherichia coli and later Staphylococcus aureus and Salmonella typhimurium. Initially, Demerec performed research using penicillin, aureomycin, and streptomycin to examine bacterial mutation and the genetic basis of antibiotic. He carried these interest into the 1950s, branching out into the mutagenic effects of a variety of salts and organic chemicals, with his final projects, conducted with Philip Hartman, involving study of the fine structure and recombination of genes in Salmonella.
Upon reaching the standard age of retirement, Demerec was replaced as Director at Cold Spring by Arthur Chovnick, who offered Demerec room for research only if he agreed to work with Chovnick's group. As a result, Demerec declined, becoming a senior staff member at Brookhaven National Labortory for five years, 1960-1965, where continued to work on problems in mutation and linkage in Salmonella. Having reached the age of mandatory retirement at Brookhaven, Demerec accepted a position as research professor at C. W. Post College of Long Island University, but died of a heart attack before he assumed the post.
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
Advances in Genetics Manuscripts (3 folders) 1949-1968
American Association for Reconstruction in Yugoslavia Records (7 folders) 1945-1957
American Cancer Society Correspondence (26 items) 1957-1960
American Naturalist Correspondence (23 items) 1936-1958
American Society of Naturalists Records (119 items) 1946-1956
Anderson, Ernest Gustav Correspondence (30 items) 1924-1931
Babcock, Ernest Brown Correspondence (22 items) 1930-1946
Beadle, George Wells Correspondence (33 items) 1929-1958
Blakeslee, Albert Francis Correspondence (6 folders) 1927-1944
Bridges, Calvin B. Correspondence (7 folders) 1932-1949
Brookhaven National Laboratory Records (5 folders) 1959-1966
Bush, Vannevar Correspondence (14 items) 1939-1956
Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory. Biological Laboratory Records (4 folders) 1940-1962
Cook, Robert C. Correspondence (118 items) 1928-1953
Davenport, Charles Benedict Correspondence (45 items) 1921-1942
Demerec, Milislav -- Cancer research Manuscripts (12 folders) 1946-1957
Demerec, Milislav -- Conferences Records (21 folders) 1939-1965
Demerec, Milislav -- Fellowships Correspondence (42 items) 1935-1941
Demerec, Milislav -- Laboratory notes Notebooks (1.5 linear feet) Circa 1930s-1940s
Demerec, Milislav -- Lectures Manuscripts (49 folders) 1930-1966
Demerec, Milislav -- Other appointments Correspondence (50 items) 1942-1957
Demerec, Milislav -- Penicillin project Correspondence (5 folders) 1942-1947
Demerec, Milislav -- Recommendations Correspondence (22 folders) 1939-1966
Demerec, Milislav -- Reprints Manuscripts (6 volumes) 1921-1968
Demerec, Milislav -- South America Correspondence (72 items) 1958-1962
Demerec, Milislav -- Travel - Australia Correspondence (70 items) 1961-1964
Demerec, Milislav -- Travel - Yugoslavia Correspondence (31 items) 1963
Demerec, Milislav -- Ultraviolet rays Manuscripts (5 folders) 1938-1940
Demerec, Milislav -- War Research. Bacterial Resistance Project Correspondence (47 items) 1939-1947
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Correspondence (172 items) 1929-1957
Drosophila Information Service Reports (2 folders) 1934-1960
Drosophila Stock Center Records (2 folders) 1934-1943
Dunn, Leslie Clarence Correspondence (35 items) 1933-1955
Emerson, Rollins Adams Correspondence (110 items) 1923-1947
Ephrussi, Boris Correspondence (40 items) 1934-1961
Fano, Ugo Correspondence (20 items) 1940-1950
Genetics Correspondence (2 folders) 1944-1966
Genetics Society of America Correspondence (2 folders) 1937-1949
Gilbert, Walter M. Correspondence (38 items) 1926-1945
Hanson, Frank Blair Correspondence (32 items) 1924-1944
Hartman, Philip E. Correspondence (8 folders) 1963-1966
Haskins, Caryl P. Correspondence (26 items) 1959-1960
Hollaender, Alexander Correspondence (75 items) 1939-1958
International Congress of Genetics. Eighth Congress Records (6 folders) 1945-1960
International Congress of Genetics. Tenth Congress Records (7 folders) 1952-1957
Kikkawa, Hideo Correspondence (26 items) 1934-1957
Koller, Peo Charles Correspondence (71 items) 1937-1960
Komai, Taku Correspondence (29 items) 1928-1956
Koric, Mirko Correspondence (46 items) 1922-1952
Kvakan, Paul Correspondence (76 items) 1923-1940
Long Island University Correspondence (25 items) 1960-1966
Mayr, Ernst Correspondence (16 items) 1944-1952
Metz, Charles W. Correspondence (4 folders) 1920-1955
Muller, Hermann Joseph Correspondence (70 items) 1926-1948
National Academy of Sciences -- Proceedings Correspondence (4 folders) 1952-1966
National Council of American-Soviet Friendship. Science Committee Records (3 folders) 1944-1946
National Research Council. Panel on genetic effects of radiation Records (2 folders) 1943-1957
National Research Council. Radiation committee Correspondence (19 items) 1929-1932
National Research Council -- RCA Fellowship Correspondence (23 items) 1940-1941
National Science Foundation Correspondence (4 folders) 1953-1966
Rhoades, Marcus M. Correspondence (26 items) 1931-1939
Schultz, Jack Correspondence (23 items) 1934-1954
Shull, George Harrison Correspondence (30 items) 1920-1938
Stadler, Lewis John Correspondence (47 items) 1926-1949
Stern, Curt Correspondence (51 items) 1930-1955
Sturtevant, Alfred Henry Correspondence (45 items) 1926-1943
Tavcar, Alois Correspondence (35 items) 1924-1960
Timofeeff-Ressovsky, Nikolai W. Correspondence (46 items) 1930-1948
Tuve, Merle Antony Correspondence (35 items) 1936-1940
Union of American Biological Societies Correspondence (57 items) 1943-1952
Wright, Sewall Correspondence (17 items) 1922-1939
American Society of Naturalists.; Babcock, E. B. (Ernest Brown), b. 1877; Bateson, Beatrice; Blakeslee, Albert Francis,1874-1954.; Bridges, Calvin B. (Calvin Blackman), 1889-1938; Bronk, Detlev W., (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975; Caspari, Ernst W.; Castle, William E., (William Ernest), 1867-1962; Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory.; Condon, Edward Uhler, 1902-1974; Davenport, Charles Benedict, 1866-1944; Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975; Emerson, Rollins Adams, 1873-1947; Ephrussi, Boris, 1901-1979; Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict, 1878-1958; Haldane, J. B. S. (John Burdon Sanderson), 1892-1964; Hollaender, Alexander, 1898-1986; Metz, Charles William, 1889-1975; Moe, Henry Allen, 1894-1975; Muller, H. J., (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967; Sonneborn, T.M., (Tracy Morton), 1905-1981; Timofeev-Resovskiĭ, N. V., (Nikolaĭ Vladimirovich), 1900-1981; Urey, Harold Clayton, 1893-1981; Antibiotics; Certificates.; Chemical mutagenesis.; Diplomas.; Drosophila--Genetics; Genetics--Research; Lectures; Maize--Genetics; Mutagens; Mutation (Biology); Notebooks; Penicillin; Photographs; Plant genetics; Radiogenetics
- Series I. Correspondence
  Scope and Contents note
  Professional correspondence of the geneticist, Milislav Demerec, pertaining largely to his research interests in the genetics of Drosophila, x-ray mutagenesis, environmental mutagenesis, and the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory.
  - Abramson, H. A., 1945-1946; 6 items (Box 1)
  - Academic Press, Inc., 1950-1956; 4 items (Box 1)
  - Ackerman, Edward A., 1960; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Adams, C. C., 1946; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Adams, Hazel, 1959; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Adams, O. R., 1957; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Adams, Walter S., 1940; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Adelberg, Edward A., 1960-1964; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Ademic, Louis, 1989-1946; 4 items (Box 1)
  - Advances in Genetics. Reviews, 1949-1968; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Publication -- Advances in Genetics; Reviews
    - Folder 1, 1949-1961; 28 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, 1954-1958; 39 items (Box 1)
  - Advances in Genetics. Royalty statements, 1962-1964; 22 items (Box 1)
    Business; Publication -- Advances in Genetics
  - Akerman, A., 1952; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Jerome, 1942; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Alikhanian, S. I., 1962; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Allen, C. E., 1928-1926; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Altenburg, Edgar, 1944-1957; 10 items (Box 1)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1959; 9 items (Box 1)
  - American Association for Reconstruction in Yugoslavia., 1945-1957; 7 folders (Box 1)
    Political issues -- Yugoslavia; World War II -- Yugoslavia
    - Folder 1, 1945-1947; 34 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, 1946-1951; 26 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 3, 1847-1948; 6 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 4, 1946; 7 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 5, 1945; 15 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 6, 1946-1947; 9 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 7, 1945-1946; 18 items (Box 1)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1944-1951; 11 items (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Women, 1958; 1 item (Box 1)
  - American Cancer Society, 1947; 1 item (Box 1)
    Cancer, chemotherapy; Committee activities -- Reports; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs
  - American Cancer Society grant, 1957-1960, 1956-1961; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Business -- Grant proposals; Cancer, chemotherapy; Research support; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs
    - Folder 1, 1959-1960; 16 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, 1956-1961; 15 items (Box 1)
  - American Cyanamid Company, 1956; 1 item (Box 1)
  - American Export Lines, Inc., 1953; 1 item (Box 1)
  - American Foundation Studies, 1955; 3 items (Box 1)
  - American Genetics Association, 1944-1945; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Folder 1, 1944; 2 items (Box 1)
    - Folder 2, 1945; 1 item (Box 1)
  - American Institute of Biological Sciences, 1949-1951; 4 items (Box 1)
  - American Institute of Physics, 1942-1944; 9 items (Box 1)
  - American Journal of Botany, 1945-1955; 12 items (Box 1)
  - American Medical Association, 1948; 2 items (Box 1)
  - American Men of Science, 1942-1949; 4 items (Box 1)
  - American Naturalist, 1936-1958; 23 items (Box 1)
    Bacterial genetics; Publication -- American Naturalist; Referee's report -- American Naturalist
  - American Philosophical Society, 1952-1960; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Folder 1, 1959-1960; 13 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 2, 1952-1959; 21 item (Box 2)
  - American Phytopathological Society, 1921; 1 item (Box 2)
  - American Society of Human Genetics, 1952-1954; 5 items (Box 2)
  - American Society of Naturalists, 1946-1956; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Conferences and symposia -- Bacterial genetics; Conferences and symposia -- Bacteriophage and viral genetics; Publication; Scientific organizations, meetings, programs
    - Folder 1, 1950-1956; 23 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 2, 1946-1954; 13 items (Box 2)
  - American Society of Naturalists. Joint Symposium. 1947, 1947-1949; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Folder 1, 1947-1949; 26 items (Box 2)
    - Folder 2, 1947; 53 items (Box 2)
  - American Society of Zoologists, 1949-1960; 4 items (Box 2)